<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Physics | Codaholic]]></title>
  <link href="http://srikumarks.github.com/blog/categories/physics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://srikumarks.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-13T16:49:32+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://srikumarks.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Srikumar]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Photon polarization]]></title>
    <link href="http://srikumarks.github.com/blog/2011/01/05/photon-polarization/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-05T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://srikumarks.github.com/blog/2011/01/05/photon-polarization</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://lesswrong.com/lw/pz/decoherence_as_projection/">Decoherence as projection</a> discusses photon polarization as a phenomenon that
can only be explained quantum mechanically even at the macroscopic level –</p>

<blockquote><p>"All right," you say, "that just seems weird." You pause. "So it’s probably something quantum."
Indeed it is.</p></blockquote>

<p>Not so quick I think. It is true that if you do this experiment at the
microscopic level with single photons you’ll have no classical explanation for
it – erm classical physics doesn’t know about photons to begin with.</p>

<p>At the macroscopic level though, oscillating <code>E</code> and <code>B</code> fields is adequate to
explain it. A polarizer projects the vectors along it’s polarization. So in the
“3 filters at 45 degrees” case you get two projections. The fields are
oscillating in a specific direction after passing through the first filter, say
with amplitude <code>E</code>. When it hits the second filter, the projected component is
simply <code>E cos 45</code>. This projected vector is now oscillating along the second
polarizer’s direction. When this hits the third filter this gets projected
again and becomes <code>E cos 45 cos 45</code>. So the final amplitude has an energy that is
<code>pow(cos 45, 4)</code> which is ¼. That is exactly what the quantum explanation gives.</p>

<p>What macroscopic aspect of plane polarization does the above explanation not cover?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
