<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: javascript | Codaholic]]></title>
  <link href="http://srikumarks.github.com/blog/categories/javascript/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://srikumarks.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-21T12:53:14+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://srikumarks.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Srikumar]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A critique of Tuna]]></title>
    <link href="http://srikumarks.github.com/blog/2012/11/09/a-critique-of-tuna/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://srikumarks.github.com/blog/2012/11/09/a-critique-of-tuna</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Google has open sourced the <a href="http://github.com/Dinahmoe/tuna">Tuna</a> set of effects used in their <a href="http://www.google.com/?q=jam+with+chrome">Jam with Chrome</a>
project. Here, I collect some thoughts about the code design decisions for their
effects framework, since I myself have written <a href="http://github.com/srikumarks/steller">Steller</a>.</p>

<h2>Parameters</h2>

<p>In Tuna, the effects module's parameters are presented to the API user as
object properties and implemented using getters and setters. This is obviously
simple from the perspective of a module user. However, it has several disadvantages -</p>

<p>If a module contains another module and you want to expose that parameter,
you're forced to write another getter/setter to handle the indirection. Such
parameters cannot be passed around "by reference". The only thing you can
do with them is to set/get their values. "By reference" passing is a simple
way to expose an internal module's parameters to the module user which is an
important kind of composability.</p>

<p>Owing to the getter/setter approach, meta information about parameters such as
their range, defaults, automation capabilities, etc. need to be stored elsewhere
in a "defaults" object, instead of being directly associated with them.</p>

<p>In some of the effects, some internal values and other parameters need to be
recomputed when a couple of parameters change. In this case, the code for
updating the dependent parameters is duplicated since it is not particularly
convenient to write a shared function local when defining parameters using
<code>Object.create</code> like this -</p>

<p>``` js</p>

<pre><code>//...
baseFrequency: {
    enumerable: true,
    get: function () {return this._baseFrequency},
    set: function (value) {
        this._baseFrequency = 50 * Math.pow(10, value * 2);
        this._excursionFrequency = Math.min(this.sampleRate / 2, this.baseFrequency * Math.pow(2, this._excursionOctaves));
        this.filterBp.frequency.value = this._baseFrequency + this._excursionFrequency * this._sweep;
        this.filterPeaking.frequency.value = this._baseFrequency + this._excursionFrequency * this._sweep;
    }
}, 
excursionOctaves: {
    enumerable: true,
    get: function () {return this._excursionOctaves},
    set: function (value) {
        this._excursionOctaves = value;
        this._excursionFrequency = Math.min(this.sampleRate / 2, this.baseFrequency * Math.pow(2, this._excursionOctaves));
        this.filterBp.frequency.value = this._baseFrequency + this._excursionFrequency * this._sweep;
        this.filterPeaking.frequency.value = this._baseFrequency + this._excursionFrequency * this._sweep;
    }
}, 
//...
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>A simpler way to solve this would be to have parameters be first class objects
that can be inspected, instead of just accessing and setting their values. Meta
data about them can travel along with them. In <a href="http://github.com/srikumarks/steller">Steller</a>, watcher functions can
be installed on parameters run code when the parameter's value changes.</p>

<h2>Inheritance using the <code>prototype</code> mechanism</h2>

<p>One of the code design choices that vastly complicates the code in this case
is the choice of using <code>prototype</code> based inheritance to define the properties
of instantiated effects modules. While this is common in the JS world,
in this case it deprives the programmer of a local context in which to hide
internal objects from the effects module's user and to write shared private
code like in the case above. Any potential loss of efficiency in not using
the prototype mechanism for this application is insignificant since object
creation is not the thing we should be optimising for.</p>

<p>The "define all methods and properties within the constructor function"
approach is much more suitable in this situation.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On eval and evil.]]></title>
    <link href="http://srikumarks.github.com/blog/2012/08/28/on-eval-being-evil/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-28T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://srikumarks.github.com/blog/2012/08/28/on-eval-being-evil</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>"eval is evil" has become a maxim repeated in the Javascript community.
Douglas Crockford, in <a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/9780596517748.do">Javascript: The Good Parts</a>, rightly advises against
hidden and explicit uses of eval for security and clarity reasons. Now, I find
<code>eval</code> useful to implement <a href="/gyan/2012/04/14/creating-dsls-in-javascript-using-j-expressions/">DSLs in Javascript</a>. The in-browser <a href="http://coffeescript.org">CoffeeScript</a>
compiler wouldn't be possible without <code>eval</code> (directly or indirectly). So, in
this post, I wish to explore what appears interesting about <code>eval</code> that is
relevant to building such DSLs.</p>

<p>For this post, I'll stick to the behaviour of <code>eval</code> in the <strong>Chrome</strong> browser
(i.e. the V8 engine, which also applies to <a href="http://nodejs.org">Node.js</a>). We'll go through a
number of contexts and examine how <code>eval</code> behaves in each of those. You can
copy paste the code shown here to Chrome's JS console and run them.</p>

<h2>What is <code>eval</code>?</h2>

<p>A simplistic description is that you pass a Javascript string to <code>eval</code> and it
will "evaluate" it as Javascript code, whatever that means. The <a href="http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-262.htm">ECMA-262</a>
specification (edition 5.1) has the following to say on <code>eval</code> -</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>10.4.2 Entering Eval Code</strong></p>

<p>The following steps are performed when control enters the execution context for
eval code:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>If there is no calling context or if the eval code is not being evaluated by
a direct call (15.1.2.1.1) to the eval function then,</p>

<p> a. Initialise the execution context as if it was a global execution context
 using the eval code as C as described in 10.4.1.1.</p></li>
<li><p>Else,</p>

<p> a. Set the <code>ThisBinding</code> to the same value as the <code>ThisBinding</code> of the calling
 execution context.</p>

<p> b. Set the LexicalEnvironment to the same value as the <code>LexicalEnvironment</code>
 of the calling execution context.</p>

<p> c. Set the <code>VariableEnvironment</code> to the same value as the <code>VariableEnvironment</code>
 of the calling execution context.</p></li>
<li><p>If the eval code is strict code, then</p>

<p> a. Let <code>strictVarEnv</code> be the result of calling <code>NewDeclarativeEnvironment</code>
 passing the <code>LexicalEnvironment</code> as the argument.</p>

<p> b. Set the <code>LexicalEnvironment</code> to <code>strictVarEnv</code>.</p>

<p> c. Set the <code>VariableEnvironment</code> to <code>strictVarEnv</code>.</p></li>
<li><p>Perform <em>Declaration Binding Instantiation</em> as described in 10.5 using the
eval code.</p></li>
</ol>


<p><strong>10.4.2.1 Strict Mode Restrictions</strong></p>

<p>The eval code cannot instantiate variable or function bindings in the variable
environment of the calling context that invoked the eval if either the code of
the calling context or the eval code is strict code. Instead such bindings are
instantiated in a new VariableEnvironment that is only accessible to the eval
code.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Introducing local variables</h2>

<p>An expression of the form <code>eval("var x = 10;")</code> is capable of introducing a new
variable <code>x</code> in the context in which it is executed. However, as noted in the
ECMA specification, if the eval code is strict, then you cannot introduce a new
variable this way - i.e. <code>eval("var x = 10;")</code> will work, but
<code>eval('"use strict"; var x = 10;')</code> will not work. No exception is thrown, but the
variable is simply not introduced into the enclosing environment, though it is
available to the rest of the evaled code.</p>

<p>Consider the following function -</p>

<p>``` js
function localVars(x, stmt) {</p>

<pre><code>eval(stmt);
return x + y;
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>All of the following behave as one might expect -</p>

<ol>
<li><code>localVars(10, "var y = 5;")</code> returns <code>15</code></li>
<li><code>localVars(10, "var y = x + 5;")</code> returns <code>25</code>.</li>
<li><code>localVars(10, "'use strict'; var y = 5;")</code> raises a <code>ReferenceError: y is not defined</code> exception.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Capturing local variables in closures</h2>

<p>Consider the following function -</p>

<p>``` js
function captureSecretValue(code) {</p>

<pre><code>var secret = 3.14159;
return eval(code);
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p><code>captureSecretValue("secret")</code> returns <code>3.14159</code> as expected. You can also
create closures that capture the "secret" value -</p>

<p><code>js
var f = captureSecretValue("(function (x) { return secret * x; })");
console.log(f(1)); // prints "3.14159"
</code></p>

<p>However, the following gives a <code>ReferenceError</code> -</p>

<p>``` js
function nest(code) {</p>

<pre><code>var nestedSecret = 2;
return eval(code);
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>function captureNestedSecret(code, nest) {</p>

<pre><code>var secret = 3.14159;
return nest(code);
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>console.log(captureNestedSecret("secret * nestedSecret", nest));
```</p>

<p>This illustrates that only the variables in the <em>lexical</em> context are available
to <code>eval</code> and not those in its <em>evaluation</em> context. The following will
therefore print <code>6.28318</code> as expected.</p>

<p>``` js
function captureNestedSecret(code) {</p>

<pre><code>var secret = 3.14159;
function nest() {
    var nestedSecret = 2;
    return eval(code);
}
return nest();
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>console.log(captureNestedSecret("secret * nestedSecret"));
```</p>

<h2>Scope objects</h2>

<p>If you have an object whose keys give variable names and whose values give their values,
you can use <code>eval</code> in conjunction with the <code>with</code> statement (beware: evil squared!) to evaluate
code in that scope. Here is what I mean -</p>

<p>``` js
function evalInScope(scope, code) {</p>

<pre><code>with (scope) {
    return eval(code);
}
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>var scope = {a: 10, b: 20};
console.log(evalInScope(scope, "a + b")); // prints "30"
console.log(evalInScope(Math, "acos(0)")); // prints "1.5707963267948966"
```</p>

<p>What is more interesting is that you can capture the "variables" in a closure
that you create using eval as follows -</p>

<p><code>js
var f = evalInScope(scope, "(function (c) { return a + b * c; })");
console.log(f(0)); // prints "10"
console.log(f(2)); // prints "50"
</code></p>

<p>Since it is not the <em>values</em> of the variables that are being captured, but
the <em>references</em>, you can now do -</p>

<p><code>js
scope.a = 100;
console.log(f(0)); // prints "100"
</code></p>

<p>If you subsequently delete one of the variables in the <code>scope</code> object, you get
a <code>ReferenceError</code> as one might expect. The <code>scope</code> object therefore provides
access to the scope chain of the created closure. This interception is deep,
since you can introduce new variables into the scope by manipulating <code>scope</code>
as well.</p>

<p><code>js
var scope = {a: 10};
var f = evalInScope(scope, "(function (c) { return a + b * c; })");
console.log(f(0));  // ReferenceError
scope.b = 20;       // Introduce binding for "b".
console.log(f(0));  // prints "10"
console.log(f(2));  // prints "50"
</code></p>

<h3>Named functions within <code>with</code></h3>

<p>The following code doesn't work and throws a <code>ReferenceError</code> because
the <code>inner</code> closure is instantiated outside the <code>with</code> scope by the V8
compiler, contrary to what it might look like.</p>

<p>``` js
// (1) doesn't work
var scope = {message: "hello world"};
var greeting;
with (scope) {</p>

<pre><code>function inner() {
    greeting = message;
}
inner();
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>The following alternative works in V8 because the closure is <em>created</em>
when executing a statement within the <code>with</code> clause.</p>

<p>``` js
// (2) works
var scope = {message: "hello world"};
var greeting;
with (scope) {</p>

<pre><code>var inner = function () {
    greeting = message;
}
inner();
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>This difference can be a WTF and points to the general recommendation of only
using the latter "name a function through assignment" approach. We know that
the definitions of named functions are lifted to the top of the surrounding
scope, but also know that they are lifted out of any surrounding <code>with</code> blocks
as well.</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>Update</strong>: This inconsistency is a bug in V8 looks like. Firefox's VM
behaves consistently in both the cases above. I've submitted a <a href="https://code.google.com/p/v8/issues/detail?id=2311">V8 bug report</a>
for this problem.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Preventing access to global objects</h2>

<p>In a browser environment, all global symbols are available as properties of the
<code>window</code> object. We can use this, in conjunction with the "scope object"
feature as discussed above, to evaluate code that is to be prevented from
touching any of these global objects or classes. This gives us a poor man's
sandbox.</p>

<p>``` js
function poorMansSandbox() {</p>

<pre><code>// arguments[0] is the code string to be evaluated in the sandbox.
// "allowed" contains all the permitted symbols for the code. (This is
// an incomplete list.)
var allowed = { "eval":     true
              , "Math" :    true
              , "Object":   true
              , "Array":    true
              , "Function": true
              , "String":   true
              , "Date":     true
              , "Number":   true
              };

// "inScope" contains all the visible definitions for the code.
// Make sure the symbols "inScope" and "allowed" are themselves not visible.
var inScope = { inScope: undefined
              , allowed: undefined 
              , poorMansSandbox: undefined
              };

// We need to run the eval in a separate function scope with
// a properly bound "this" because otherwise "this" will be
// the "window" object and all our efforts will have been in vain.
// We make "this" the scope object itself (i.e. "inScope")
return (function () {
    Object.getOwnPropertyNames(window).forEach(function (g) {
        if (!allowed[g]) {
            inScope[g] = undefined;
        }
    });
    with (inScope) {
        return eval(arguments[0]);
    }
}).call(inScope, arguments[0]);
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Though this prevents access to existing global properties, it doesn't prevent
access to properties that will be added to <code>window</code> <em>after</em> the <code>eval</code> happens.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p><code>eval</code> should be used with tons of caution. However, if you're interested in
making DSLs around Javascript, it helps to know its workings a bit deeper.
Remember - there is always something "good" in every "evil" ;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Toy language using j-expressions]]></title>
    <link href="http://srikumarks.github.com/blog/2012/04/30/toy-language-using-j-expressions/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-30T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://srikumarks.github.com/blog/2012/04/30/toy-language-using-j-expressions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Posted a "stream of thought" compiler for a toy language based
on the idea of j-expressions as a representation for ASTs.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://github.com/srikumarks/jexpr">Code</a></li>
<li><a href="http://srikumarks.github.com/jexpr">Docs</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[J-expressions]]></title>
    <link href="http://srikumarks.github.com/blog/2012/04/15/j-expressions/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-15T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://srikumarks.github.com/blog/2012/04/15/j-expressions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.json.org">JSON</a> has become a kind of de-facto standard for sharing data among services
on the web. The Lisp folks have enjoyed this luxury ever since ... well ever
since McCarthy made the language and his student implemented an interpreter for
it. What's more, they have also had the luxury of using the same syntax for
sharing <em>logic</em> .. and in fact take it for granted. This post is a proposal to
bring that "luxury" to the web programming world.</p>

<p><strong>Status:</strong> Draft. Comments welcome.</p>

<h2>Why is it useful to be able to share logic?</h2>

<p>If you've already bought into Lisp, you may not need much convincing here.  If
you do ask that question, I've written about <a href="/gyan/2012/04/14/creating-dsls-in-javascript-using-j-expressions">DSLs and J-expressions</a> in an
earlier post that may be of interest to you.</p>

<h2>Core syntax</h2>

<ol>
<li><p>A "J-expression" is an ordinary JSON-serializeable <strong>object</strong>, whose "first
key" is taken to name an "operator", with the whole object serving as its
"operand".</p></li>
<li><p>A J-expression's key <strong>must</strong> be an identifier conforming to the following
regular expression</p>

<pre><code> (Letter|$|_)(Letter|DecimalDigit|$|_)*
</code></pre></li>
<li><p>We permit an extension to JSON whereby the key <strong>need not</strong> be a <em>quoted</em>
string.  Nevertheless, a key <strong>must</strong> conform to the above regular expression
even when quoted.</p></li>
<li><p>Everything else -- numbers, strings, dates and arrays -- is just as
specified in <a href="http://www.json.org">JSON</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>We leave the question of how the "operator" must use the operands open in
order to allow for eager and lazy computations, and meta-expressions.</p></li>
<li><p>Every J-expression <strong>may</strong> have a <code>comment</code> key whose value is for human
consumption and is therefore expected to have nil impact on the meaning of
the expression to a program.  It <strong>may</strong> therefore be ignored by parsers
and interpreters. J-expression writers, however, <strong>must</strong> strip out these
comment fields before serializing these expressions. This means <code>comment</code>
is a "reserved key".</p></li>
<li><p>Every J-expression <strong>may</strong> have a <code>meta</code> key whose value is a <a href="http://www.json.org">JSON</a> value
and is considered of some relevance to the system processing the script.
This could include additional documentation references, version information,
source URL for a specification of the operator, etc.  ..  the structure of
which is left unspecified. J-expression writers, therefore, <strong>must not</strong>
strip out the <code>meta</code> entry. This means <code>meta</code> is a "reserved key".</p></li>
</ol>


<h4>An example</h4>

<p>``` js</p>

<pre><code>{do: [
    {fetchURL: "http://some.data.source/",
      timeout: 30.0,
       onfail: {raiseError: "URL not reachable"}},
    {fork: [
        {displayInElement: "element_id"},
        {cacheInLocalStorage: "prefix"}
        ]}]}
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>The above script can be read as representing a "pipe" where the
data is fetched from some URL and then (concurrently) displayed
in an element and cached in local storage.</p>

<h3>Some considerations</h3>

<ol>
<li><p>J-expression parsers are expected to be support both quoted and
unquoted keys in order to enable "logic" and "data" to take the
same form.</p></li>
<li><p>J-expression writers are also allowed to use either form, but writing
unquoted keys is preferred since it is more compact than quoted keys and
closer in form to the notion of "programming" or "scripting".</p></li>
</ol>


<h4>The "first key" as the "operator"</h4>

<p>Javascript implementations today preserve the order in which keys are inserted
into objects when traversing keys as long as the keys are not array indices.
Even when the specification does not require them to do so, Google considers it
a de-facto standard that insertion and enumeration order must match whenever
only string keys are involved - as noted in this <a href="http://code.google.com/p/v8/issues/detail?id=164">V8 bug</a>. This de-facto
standard permits easy identification of the "first key" in a JSON expression as
shown below --</p>

<p>``` js</p>

<pre><code>function jexpr_operator(jexpr) {
    for (var first_key in jexpr) {
        return first_key;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>In languages such as <a href="http://www.python.org">Python</a>, <a href="http://ruby-lang.org">Ruby</a> and <a href="http://www.lua.org">Lua</a>, we cannot assume that the
first key can be so easily identified, but since all these languages have
custom syntax checking parsers for scanning JSON, it is a trivial extension to
the parser to add a special key to an object to help identify the first key.</p>

<blockquote><p>The key <code>__jexpr_operator__</code> is reserved for parsers so that they can
indicate what the "first key" is by giving its name as the value of this key.
For the rest of the system, the presence of this key overrides any key order
already obeyed by the system. J-expression writers must use this key to
determine which key to write first, but <strong>must not</strong> output this key itself.</p></blockquote>

<p>Parsers in languages with objects that do not preserve identity between key
insertion and enumeration order can add a small bit of logic to insert the
above special key.</p>

<p>``` js</p>

<pre><code>function jexpr_operator(jexpr) {
    if ("__jexpr_operator__" in jexpr) {
        return jexpr.__jexpr_operator__;
    } else {
        for (var first_key in jexpr) {
            return first_key;
        }
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Beyond this, we do not need the order of the other keys to be preserved and
operator implementations should not make that assumption.</p>

<h2>Can we build programming languages using j-expressions?</h2>

<p>It sure looks possible to do so. For example, here is a (toy) compiler for
<a href="https://github.com/srikumarks/jexpr">J a Scheme-like language</a> that is about as expressive as Scheme .. except for the
lack of support for tail call elimination.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating DSLs in Javascript using J-expressions]]></title>
    <link href="http://srikumarks.github.com/blog/2012/04/14/creating-dsls-in-javascript-using-j-expressions/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-14T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://srikumarks.github.com/blog/2012/04/14/creating-dsls-in-javascript-using-j-expressions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Scheme and Lisp have for long had powerful meta-programming abilities due to
the syntax of their language being the same as the syntax for the main data
structure supported by the language - the humble list. These languages are
therefore well suited for inventing smaller special purpose "domain specific
languages.</p>

<p>Javascript, on the other hand, has a "full blown syntax" that makes
meta-programming not for the faint of heart. One consequence of the lack of
such ability is that developers have not had the benefit of the abstraction
possible through small special purpose DSLs.</p>

<p>Here, I outline an approach for creating DSLs in Javascript using the now
prevalent <a href="http://www.json.org">JSON</a> format that is native to the language. The initial part tries
to explain the kinds of scenarios in which one might consider building a DSL,
which is important to have an idea about. Later, I get into the actual
representation using JSON.</p>

<h2>When to make a DSL? .. or "Hunting of the Closure".</h2>

<p>Under normal circumstances, you should consider developing your abstractions as
"modules". Modules (or "libraries") offer basic encapsulation and hiding
facilities that JS developers are familiar with. You can help them benefit from
your work by leveraging that familiarity.</p>

<p>On the rare occasion though, you might find yourself writing code that starts
looking like a small "compiler"  or "runtime". In such circumstances, creating
a DSL for that part of the system might be worthwhile to consider -- the purpose,
again, being that it might ease the job of those that your package targets.</p>

<p>A tipping point can happen when you discover that you are working with a
category of objects that are "closed over" a suite of operations.  In
mathematics, a set of objects is said to be "closed" with respect to a function
if the function maps objects of the set to other objects in the same set and we
say the set "has the closure property". But before we get to why that's
significant, let's take a quick look at a simple example.</p>

<h3>The "closure property" - an example</h3>

<p>Say we want a framework to create and render visuals that vary in time -- like,
maybe, umm ... a video? Here is a simple representation of such a visual, which
we'll call a "show"  -</p>

<p>``` js
function show(t) {</p>

<pre><code>// calculate...
return image;
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Given such a "show", it is trivial to write a renderer for it -</p>

<p>``` js
function render(show, duration_ms) {</p>

<pre><code>var startTime_ms = Date.now();
requestAnimationFrame(function () {
    var t = Date.now() - startTime_ms;
    context.draw(show(t));
    if (t &lt; duration_ms) {
        requestAnimationFrame(arguments.callee);
    }
});
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Now, I want an operator which will delay a given show by a specified amount
of time. Simple -</p>

<p>``` js
function delay(show, dt_ms) {</p>

<pre><code>return function (t) {
    return show(t - dt_ms);
};
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>How about a "cut" from one show to another at a given time. Also simple -</p>

<p>``` js
function cut(when, show1, show2) {</p>

<pre><code>return function (t) {
    return (t &lt; when ? show1 : show2)(t);
};
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Now, if we represent video clips using such <code>show</code>s, those two functions under
which the set of <code>show</code>s is closed give us all we need to make an edited
production .... because we can combine them.  Note that <code>delay</code> takes a show
and produces a show, and so does <code>cut</code> ... which takes <em>two</em> shows, yes, but
that's the same idea. This kind of combinatorial power is valuable when
modelling a domain.</p>

<blockquote><h5>ShowTime</h5>

<p>The interface to <a href="http://www.muvee.com">muvee Reveal</a>'s rendering engine "ShowTime" is built
around this kind of an abstraction. The details of <a href="http://muvee-style-authoring.googlecode.com/svn/doc/main/ShowTime_-_the_muvee_timeline.html">ShowTime</a> and the DSL for
<a href="http://muvee-style-authoring.googlecode.com">authoring muvee's "styles"</a> built on top of this API are available publicly.
In this case, the DSL abstracts away implementation details such as the deep
nesting of functions that might result in a naive implementation.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Functions are closed under composition</h2>

<p>Here is what makes the closure property worth hunting for --</p>

<blockquote><p>When you have several functions under which your set is closed, it is also
closed under <em>arbitrary compositions</em> of these functions.</p></blockquote>

<p>So, well, why bother with a DSL? Why not just use function composition?  One
reason is that, in the real world, your set is closed with respect to each of
these functions <em>only under certain constraints</em>. These constraints might make
it difficult to predict whether a given composition of these functions is a
valid operation in your domain. You will need to validate a composition
<em>before</em> you begin to act on it, which becomes difficult if you only have
access to the composition and not the parts. A DSL that abstracts over these
constraints by exposing only that subset of compositions that are valid in the
domain would therefore be of great help to people reusing your work.</p>

<blockquote><p>The DSL's purpose, then, is to hide the constraints under which closure is
possible and composition operations are valid - i.e. where composition and
use are context sensitive.</p></blockquote>

<h2>A DSL for asynchronous operations</h2>

<p>Let's consider an example where having a DSL seems beneficial - composing
asynchronous operations.</p>

<p>It is a common convention for a function that does some asynchronous action to
accept "callback" and "errback" functions to call when it succeeds or fails
respectively.  Composing such actions into sequences soon turns into what is
usually referred to as "callback hell" and the person reading the source soon
looses sight of the whole flow of control.</p>

<p>So, do we satisfy our "DSL criteria" here?</p>

<ol>
<li>Closure property? CHECK. A sequence of operations is itself an operation.</li>
<li>Constraints? CHECK. A sequence is allowed to proceed normally only when an
operation doesn't fail. There are many error handling strategies when an
operation fails and we may not have seen all of them yet.</li>
</ol>


<p>Let's then make a small DSL for sequencing asynchronous operations.</p>

<h2>Representing asynchronous operations</h2>

<p>First we're going to need a way to define new asynchonous operations
in plain Javascript for our "primitives". A simple representation is
to model an async operation (let's call them "asop"s for convenience)
as a function that takes a specific set of arguments as follows --</p>

<p>``` js
function asop(M, input, success, failure) {</p>

<pre><code>// ...
// we're good.
M.start(success, input, M.end, M.failure);

// Something bad happened
M.start(failure, M.error("bad", input, success, failure), M.end, M.end);
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>The function takes four parameters -</p>

<ol>
<li><code>M</code> is a module that provides facilities for starting an asop --
<code>M.start</code> and a terminal operation <code>M.end</code> that does nothing and stops all
processing.</li>
<li><code>input</code> is the data being passed to the asop to do its job.</li>
<li><code>success</code> is an asop to start once this asop finishes
successfully.</li>
<li><code>failure</code> is an asop to start if this asop cannot be completed for
some reason.</li>
</ol>


<blockquote><p>Note that an asop is recursively defined in terms of and makes use of two
other asops <code>success</code> and <code>failure</code>, which themselves have the <em>same</em>
function signature.</p></blockquote>

<p>We take <code>M.error</code> to be a utility that produces an error object that captures
the current error state to pass to the failure operation. Here is a simple
definition for <code>M</code> --</p>

<p>``` js
M.start = function (op, input, succ, fail) {</p>

<pre><code>setTimeout(function () {
    op(M, input, succ, fail);
}, 0);
</code></pre>

<p>};
M.error = function (descr, input, succ, fail) {</p>

<pre><code>return new Error({descr: descr, input: input, success: succ, failure: fail});
</code></pre>

<p>},
M.end = function () {};
```</p>

<h2>Sequencing two operations</h2>

<p>Since our operations are ordinary functions, we can write a "sequencing operator"
for combining two operations as a higher order function as follows --</p>

<p>``` js
function seq(first, next) {</p>

<pre><code>return function (M, input, success, failure) {
    M.start(first, input, seq(next, success), failure);
};
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p><em>Note</em>: This looks like infinite recursion, but it will terminate automatically
when <code>M.end</code> is passed for <code>next</code> because, we define <code>M.end</code> to be the operation
that doesn't continue further.</p>

<h2>Making a chain of operations</h2>

<p>The humble <code>seq</code> operator can now be put to use to chain an arbitrary
number of operations given as an array ---</p>

<p>``` js
function chain(operations) {</p>

<pre><code>var revOps = operations.slice(0).reverse();
return function (M, input, success, failure) {
    M.start(revOps.reduce(seq, success), input, M.end, failure);
};
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<h2>Umm ... why do we need a DSL again?</h2>

<p>You'd be right in asking that question. So far, it looks like the language is
expressive enough to let us code up all these compositions using plain higher
order functions. So, let me throw something into the mix that might cause you
to stumble if you think such functions alone are adequate.</p>

<p>Consider the exchanges that happen between a web server and a client (browser).
A client instructs a web server to perform some operation, the server gets back
when done, or with progress notifications, then the client does a few async things
like store some data locally, and then makes the next request and so on. The ability
to represent a <em>sequence</em> of actions directly is a boon to take care of all these
exchanges happening between these two dance partners.</p>

<blockquote><h3>So here is your task - ###</h3>

<p>Abstract away the transaction to survive a termination of connection with the
server. I'm not talking packet loss here.  I'm talking about the user
initiating a series of operations and in the middle of things shutting down
the browser. What I want to happen is for the operations to continue exactly
from wherever they left off -- because I cannot "throw an exception" and undo
a rocket launch. If the client was waiting for a response from the server, it
should again start waiting for that response; and by implication if the
server was doing something and found out that the connection had terminated
at the "next" step, it should've stored away whatever it needed to do to
continue, and must resume that when the user connects again, maybe after some
mild handshaking. In particular, it is <em>not</em> acceptable to terminate the
operation sequence just because the browser was closed.</p></blockquote>

<p>Trying to do something like this is where reifying processes as functions
breaks down. To a lisp/scheme programmer, a solution would already be in sight
-- use s-expressions to represent operations and store away instructions in
that form. What might we do in the Javascript world?</p>

<h2>J expressions</h2>

<p>The image I have in my mind now is Douglas Crockford standing with legs apart,
arms folded, cape flying with a speech bubble pointing to his head saying
"JSON to the rescue!".</p>

<p>Since we have our framework taking care of coordinating the success and failure
of operations, all it takes to <em>specify</em> an operation, given a known set of
named "primitive" operations, are the following --</p>

<ol>
<li>The <em>name</em> of the operation to start.</li>
<li>An <em>input</em> object to customize any details of the operation.</li>
</ol>


<p>So, there you go, we can change our representation of an operation from being
a function to something that looks like -</p>

<p><code>js
{opname: input_object}
</code></p>

<p>(Technically, that'll be <code>{"opname": input_object}</code> in JSON, but let's ignore
that difference since it is <em>serializable</em> using JSON, which is what's
important.)</p>

<p>The input object is also a literal or computed <em>value</em> which we restrict to
JSON-serializable values. The named primitive operation can itself be provided
in a module as a function that takes the whole spec object and does what it is
supposed to do.</p>

<p>We can now specify a series of operations as an array in this form -</p>

<p>``` js
{do: [</p>

<pre><code>{ask: "Enter file name: ", 
    type: "file"},
{fetchFile: {showProgress: "progress_bar"},
    reportInterval: 1.0},
{spawn: {withRetry: {uploadToDropbox: {user: "cat", password: "meow"}},
            maxTries: 5,
              onfail: {do: [
                        {deleteTempFiles: null},
                        {ask: "Dropbox upload failed. Try again?", 
                            type: "yes/no",
                             yes: {retry: true},
                              no: {raise: "Give up"}}
                        ]}}},
{cacheInLocalStore: "prefix"},
{showInElement: "element_id"}
</code></pre>

<p>]}
```</p>

<p>If we are given the primitive operations as members of a module <code>M</code>, we can run
a primitive operation as follows -</p>

<p>``` js
function runPrimitiveOperation(opspec) {</p>

<pre><code>return function (M, input, success, failure) {
    for (var opname in opspec) {
        M[opname](M, opspec, input, success, failure);
        return;
    }
};
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<blockquote><h4>Note</h4>

<p>Here I'm making use of the fact that JS engines today such as V8 always
enumerate the keys of an object in the order in which they were added to it.
This is what lets us identify the <em>first</em> key as determining the operation to
start with the operation implementation knowing what to make of the other
keys in the expression, the parameters and so on.</p>

<p>Also note that we've put in a pipeline here -- i.e. <code>ask</code> gets a file name
that it passes as input to <code>fetchFile</code> which passes the fetched file data to
<code>spawn</code>, and so on. <code>spawn</code> is a higher order operation, since it takes an
operation as the argument to perform concurrently, while continuing by
passing its input through to <code>cacheInLocalStore</code>.</p></blockquote>

<p>Our framework, then, serves as an interpreter for this mini language, providing
the necessary abstractions on <em>how</em> we expect these operations to be executed
behind the scenes. What is important is that <em>users</em> of our framework are not
forced to think about browser shutdown/restart cases and can simply assume
that the infrastructure we provide will "do the right thing".</p>

<p>Now, I'm not going to go into details of what one actually needs to do to
<em>implement</em> the shutdown/restart behaviour, but at this point, it ought to be
clear enough that given a serializable representation of "operations still left
to do" and a serializable representation of the input to give to this sequence,
we can dump both at any point to disk (plus some book keeping info) and resume
after a browser/server restart. We'll need to do that for <em>each task sequence</em>
that's active at the point the shutdown is initiated.</p>

<p>The important thing is that the one writing the script can focus on writing the
script instead of the operational details.</p>

<h2>Recap</h2>

<p>The main takeaways from this post are the following -</p>

<ol>
<li><p>If you find categories of objects in your problem domain that are closed
over a number of functions and you want to abstract away the constraints
under which those functions can be combined, you may find it useful to
create a DSL for your domain.</p></li>
<li><p>The consistent implementation of key enumeration order of objects in
Javascript engines allows us to write <strong>specifications of composeable
computations</strong> using generic JSON-serializable notation that we can call
"J-expressions".</p>

<pre><code>{opname: main_parameter,
    keyword1: value1,
    keyword2: value2,
    ...}
</code></pre></li>
<li><p>J-expressions, in combination with functions that implement what the
operation named "opname" is supposed to do, are then a systematic way to
approach DSL construction within Javascript.  The notation is as expressive
as s-expressions. For instance, here is a way to write a "higher order
asop" :)</p>

<pre><code>{lambda_the_ultimate: ["arg"],
    do: [
        {step1: ..},
        {step2: ..}
    ]}
</code></pre></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
