<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Carnatic music | Codaholic]]></title>
  <link href="http://srikumarks.github.com/blog/categories/carnatic-music/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://srikumarks.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-30T10:43:31+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://srikumarks.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Srikumar]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring graha bhedams]]></title>
    <link href="http://srikumarks.github.com/blog/2012/12/30/exploring-grha-bhedams/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-30T15:43:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://srikumarks.github.com/blog/2012/12/30/exploring-grha-bhedams</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here is a <a href="/demos/bhedam">demo web app</a> for exploring rāgās and their bhēdams.</p>

<p>A few weeks ago, I had a conversation with Mr. Ramesh who showed me
some amazing Excel wizardry and spells he'd cast to be able to take
a raga and ask questions about its <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Graha_bhedam">graha bhēdams</a>. I hadn't realized
until then that the question of what the scales of ragas turn into
when you do bhēdams on them (graha or śruti bhēdam) involves a rather
non-trivial mental transformation, though one that is pretty simple
to do on a computer. So I resurrected a rāgā database that I'd scraped
off Wikipedia's <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Janya_Ragas">Janya Rāgās</a> page some 4 years ago and made this
<a href="/demos/bhedam">bhēdam explorer</a> web app.</p>

<p>The app could use some visual love, but it serves the exploratory
purpose as it stands. Have fun with it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scratch pad for text with diacritics]]></title>
    <link href="http://srikumarks.github.com/blog/2012/12/27/scratch-pad-for-text-with-diacritics/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-27T10:09:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://srikumarks.github.com/blog/2012/12/27/scratch-pad-for-text-with-diacritics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Roman text with a few choice diacritics are a common need when writing about
Indian classical music. Creating unicode text with diacritics that can be
ported between applications is in general a pain. So, I made a small in-browser
app that serves as a <a href="/demos/diacritics">scratch pad for common diacritics</a>.</p>

<h3>Usage</h3>

<p>Straight forward. You just type your text in the provided box using normal
roman characters first - ex: "Sankarabharanam". Once you've typed that in,
you select each character to which you want to apply diacritical marks and
click on the mark you want. You can also press the number key corresponding
to the diacritical mark you want for the selected character. With this,
you can get "Śankarābharaṇam".</p>

<p>Your text is automatically saved to local storage, so you can visit the page
any time and retrieve your text. You'll <em>never</em> lose text you key in.</p>

<h3>Known issues</h3>

<p>This works fine in Chrome and Safari on MacOSX, but not in Firefox. I haven't
yet figured out why it doesn't work in Firefox. If you find that it works in
Chrome/Safari on Windows/Linux, please let me know in the comments.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
